Finding aid to Robert Withington papers CA.MS.01126
Smith College Archives
Robert Withington papers
1912-1954
Smith College Archives
Withington, Robert, 1884-1957
CA.MS.01126
1.75 linear feet (4 containers)
Robert Withington was a professor of English at Smith College. These papers contain biographical material, correspondence, photographs, poetry, speeches, publications, and books.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Robert Withington papers were donated to the Smith College Archives by Helen Small Withington, Robert Withington's wife, upon his death in 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Withington was born in Boston, Massachusetts to Charles Francis Withington and Georgiana Bowen on June 7, 1884. He graduated from Roxbury Latin School in 1902 and earned his Bachelor of Arts degree at Harvard University in 1906. He also received his Master of Arts and Doctor of Philosophy degrees there in 1909 and 1913, respectively. Before he became a faculty member at Smith College, he was an English instructor at the University de Lyon, France (1909 – 1910), an assistant in English at Harvard (1910 – 1912), a Rogers travelling fellow of Harvard in Europe (1913 – 1914), and an English instructor at Indiana University (1914 - 1917). During World War I, in 1916, Withington was a member of the Hoover Relief Commission in Belgium, stationed at Antwerp and Hasselt. In 1918 - 1919, he was a captain in the A.R.C. and 2nd Lieutenant in the U.S.A. Infantry in France and served with the American Red Cross. Withington was honored in 1919 with the Chevalier de l'Ordre de la Couronne in Belgium. In 1920, he was named officier d'Academie in France and, in 1930, he was named officier de l'Instruction Publique. Withington joined the faculty at Smith College in 1917. During his time at Smith College, he spent nearly twenty years as an advisor to the Smith College Press Board. He was an assistant professor of English from 1917 to 1920. He was associate professor of English from 1920 to 1925 and professor of English from 1925 until his retirement in 1952. Withington was a frequent contributor to periodicals, specializing in the essay and early drama. H is the author of English Pageantry: a Historical Outline (vol. i, 1918; vol. ii, 1920); In Occupied Beligium, 1921; and Excursions in English Drama, 1937. He was also editor of Essays and Characters, Montaigne to Goldsmith, 1933 and Essays and Characters, Lamb to Thompson, 1933. With the late Cortlandt van Winkle, Withington co-edited Eminent British Writers of the Nineteenth Century, 1934. He was a member of the Modern Language Association, the American Association of University Professors, the Belgium American Education Foundation, and the Garrick Club, London. Withington was granted a leave of absence from Smith College for the first semester of the 1945-1946 school year to serve as a professor in the U.S. Army Education Center in Biarritz, France. Withington retired from the Smith faculty in 1952. He died at his home in 1957 following a long illness and was survived by his wife and two daughters.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Withington papers contain biographical material, correspondence, photographs, poetry, speeches, publications, and books.
Withington, Helen Small; Withington, Helen Small
- General Biography File, 1919-1954 (Box 1087, Folder 1)
- Awards, 1930; 1943 (Box 1087, Folder 2)
- Correspondence – Adams, Sherman, 1952 (Box 1087, Folder 3)
- Correspondence – Baldenspuge (?), Feman, 1950 (Box 1087, Folder 4)
- Correspondence – Caverno, Julia, 1939 (Box 1087, Folder 5)
- Correspondence – Davis, Herbert, 1941; 1944 (Box 1087, Folder 6)
- Correspondence – Ellis, Milton, 1939 (Box 1087, Folder 7)
- Correspondence – Hoover, Herbert, 1928 (Box 1087, Folder 8)
- Correspondence – Jordan, Mary Augusta, 1921 (Box 1087, Folder 9)
- Correspondence – Lanman, Charles R., 1917 (Box 1087, Folder 10)
- Correspondence – McElwain, Mary Belle, 1941; 1942 (Box 1087, Folder 11)
- Correspondence – Morrow, Elizabeth Cutter, 1937 (Box 1087, Folder 12)
- Correspondence – Notestein, Ada Comstock, 1946 (Box 1087, Folder 13)
- Correspondence – Parker, Louis N., 1912-1943 (Box 1087, Folder 14-17)
- Correspondence – Schauffler, Robert Haven, 1919 (Box 1087, Folder 18)
- Correspondence – Stevenson, George F., 1943 (Box 1087, Folder 19)
- Correspondence – to Family, 1913 (Box 1087, Folder 20)
- Correspondence – to Morrow, Elizabeth Cutter, 1940 (Box 1087, Folder 21)
- Correspondence – to Neilson, William Allan, 1924 (Box 1087, Folder 22)
- Correspondence – to Randall, Helen W., undated (Box 1087, Folder 23)
- Miscellaneous, 1930-1944 (Box 1087, Folder 24)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1087, Folder 25)
- Poetry, undated (Box 1087, Folder 26)
- Speeches, broadcasts, 1937-1938 (Box 1087, Folder 27)
- Acceleration, 1944 (Box 1088, Folder 1)
- Additional notes on modern fold pageantry, 1922 (Box 1088, Folder 2)
- The Ancestry of the "Vice", 1932 (Box 1088, Folder 3)
- Bulletins on the American Pageant Association, 1915-1917 (Box 1088, Folder 4)
- Arma Virumque, 1917 (Box 1088, Folder 5)
- Art and propaganda, 1947 (Box 1088, Folder 6)
- The Bones of Dreams, 1922 (Box 1088, Folder 7)
- Braggart, Devil, and 'Vice', 1936 (Box 1088, Folder 8)
- Bunk and Bunker Hill, 1943 (Box 1088, Folder 9)
- Censer and Censor, 1949 (Box 1088, Folder 10)
- The Color of the Ocean, 1949 (Box 1088, Folder 11)
- The Dangers of Procrustean Education, 1949 (Box 1088, Folder 12)
- The Early "Royal-Entry", 1917 (Box 1088, Folder 13)
- Experience, the Mother of Science, 1942 (Box 1088, Folder 14)
- F.S. which is to say …, 1925 (Box 1088, Folder 15)
- The Failure of our Civilization, 1948 (Box 1088, Folder 16)
- A French Comment on the Battle of Bunker Hill, 1949 (Box 1088, Folder 17)
- Irving, Hazlitt, and the New Criticism, 1951 (Box 1088, Folder 18)
- The Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 1932 (Box 1088, Folder 19)
- The Legacy of the Great, 1943 (Box 1088, Folder 20)
- The Lord Mayor's Show for 1590, 1918 (Box 1088, Folder 21)
- Mak, Op-Signorken, and Mr. Hardwick, 1949 (Box 1088, Folder 22)
- The Marquis de Chastellux on Language and Peace, 1943 (Box 1088, Folder 23)
- Missionaries in Reverse, 1942 (Box 1088, Folder 24)
- Modern Trends in Education, 1935 (Box 1088, Folder 25)
- My Neece Plantagenet, 1932 (Box 1088, Folder 26)
- More "Portmanteau" Coinages, 1932 (Box 1088, Folder 27)
- Notes on Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress (Box 1088, Folder 28)
- Of College Colors, 1947 (Box 1088, Folder 29)
- On Names, Euphonious and Other, 1947 (Box 1088, Folder 30)
- Other "Portmanteau" Words, 1925 (Box 1088, Folder 31)
- Poetry: Body and Soul, 1917 (Box 1088, Folder 32)
- Of the Eleventh Commandment, 1926 (Box 1088, Folder 33)
- On College Debating, 1928 (Box 1088, Folder 34)
- Reviews and criticisms, 1937 (Box 1088, Folder 35)
- Roman Time, 1943 (Box 1088, Folder 36)
- Scott's Contribution to Pageantic Development, 1920 (Box 1088, Folder 37)
- Shakespeare and Race Prejudice, 1945 (Box 1088, Folder 38)
- Some Lessons from Biarritz, 1946 (Box 1088, Folder 39)
- The State of the Theatre: Hits and Misses, 1951 (Box 1088, Folder 40)
- That These May Eat, 1917 (Box 1088, Folder 41)
- Verbal Pungencies, 1939 (Box 1088, Folder 42)
- "Vice and Parasite" correspondence in re:, 1934 (Box 1088, Folder 43)
- In Occupied Belgium, 1921 (Box 1088)
- American Association University Professors Bulletin, 1946 (Box 1088)
- English pageantry correspondence, 1912-1952 (Box 1089, Folder 1)
- English pageantry cuts, lithographs, 1918 (Box 1089, Folder 2)
- English pageantry general, 1915 (Box 1089, Folder 3)
- English Pageantry, Volume 1, 1918 (Box 1089)
- English Pageantry, Volume 2, 1920 (Box 1089)
- British Poetry and Prose, Part 1, 1928 (Box 1090)
- Writing of Today (Box 1090)
- Shakespeare's Principal Plays (Box 1090)
- English 316 notes on the essay (Box 1090)
- Robert Withington, Ph.D. notebook (Box 1090)
- British Poets of the Nineteenth Century Page (Box 1090)
- Century Readings in English Literature, volume 1 (Box 1090)
- Century Readings in English Literature, volume 1 (Box 1090)
- Century Readings in English Literature, volume 1 (Box 1090)
- Chaucer Man of Lawe (Box 1090)
- Chaucer Progresses Tales (Box 1090)